A Guide to the Richmond City (Va.) Business Records, 1828-1917
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Richmond City (Va.) Business Records, 1828-1917
Library of Virginia
43 volumes and .10 cubic feet.
Richmond City (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Many of the business volumes are fragile and should not be handled. please check alternative form available heading for volumes that have been microfilmed. Please use microfilm if available.
Acquisition Information
These records came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Richmond City in 1997, 2000 and 2024 under accession numbers 37365, 37367, 37369 and 37380.
Historical Information
Context for Record Type: Business Records, both volumes and loose records are in some cases transferred to the Library of Virginia as components of court record transfers. These business records in some cases were simply stored in the local court building for safekeeping by business owners. In other cases, business records (particularly ledgers, account books, etc.) may have been filed in a court case as an exhibit. These business records exhibit appeared both in chancery causes and in judgments. These records serving as exhibits for business dissolution cases, debt suits, and contract disputes.
Locality History: Richmond, located between Henrico and Chesterfield Counties, was named by William Byrd (1674-1744), who envisioned the development of a city at the falls of the James River and with the help of William Mayo laid out the town in 1737. The name probably came from the English borough of Richmond upon Thames, which Byrd visited on several occasions. Richmond was established in 1742 and in 1779 was designated the capital of Virginia effective 30 April 1780. It was incorporated as a town, although "stiled the city of Richmond," in 1782 and was incorporated as a city in 1842. It served as the capital of the Confederacy from mid-1861 to April 1865. Richmond was enlarged by the annexation of Manchester (or South Richmond) in 1910, and by the addition of Barton Heights, Fairmount, and Highland Park in 1914. Further annexations from Chesterfield County occurred in 1942 and 1970.
Lost Records Note: During the burning of Richmond on April 3, 1865, during the Civil War, Richmond circuit court judge John A. Meredith led efforts to save the circuit court records found at the State Court House. Rescuers successfully removed all the papers that were necessary to pending suits and many of the order books, but all of the wills and deed books were lost. Records of the superior court and circuit superior court of law and chancery were also destroyed. Most of the pre-Civil War Hustings Court records exist.
Scope and Content
Richmond City (Va.) Business Records, 1828-1917, is comprised of various records created by individuals and companies is pursuit of documenting business activities in and around Richmond City (Va.). Represented records largerly consists of bound volumes such as ledgers, daybooks, stock book, minute books, account books, receipt books, cashbooks, journals, and letter books.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged
Series I: Bowman and Stroock Receipt Books, 1865-1867
Series II: Clarkson Anderson and Company Ledger, 1859-1867
Series III: Commonwealth Bank of Richmond Receivers' Cashbook, 1913-1917
Series IV: First National Bank Ledger, 1871-1877
Series V: Jacob Shook Daybook, 1828-1832
Series VI: James Murphy Ledger, 1859-1873
Series VII: Lisburn Land Company Minute Book, 1890-1901
Series VIII: Mechanics Building Company Journal No. 3, 1877-1886
Series IX: National Auto Schools Corporation Stock Book, 1911
Series X: Old Dominion Electrical Construction Company Ledger, 1895-1896
Series XI: R.H. Boykin and Company Letterbook, 1895
Series XII: Richmond Wood Ware Manufacturing Company Business Records, 1894
Series XIII: Robert Nowlan Macomber Checkbook, 1912-1914
Series XIV: Samuel P. Lathrop Checkbook, 1878
Series XV: Turner Brooks and Company Account Book, 1869
Series XVI: Unidentified Cashbook, 1887-1889
Series XVII: Unidentified Cashbook, 1888-1891
Series XVIII: Unidentified Checkbook, 1865-1866
Series XIX: Unidentified Grocer Ledger, 1890
Series XX: Unidentified Ledger of Northern Accounts, 1890
Series XXI: Unidentified Liquor Dealer Ledger, 1912-1913
Series XXII: Unidentified Profit and Loss Ledger, 1911-1913
Series XXIII: Unidentified Restaurant and Ice Cream Parlor Daybook, 1911
Series XXIV: Virginia Manufacturing and Trading Company Minute Book, 1882-1884
Series XXV: Virginia Marl Phosphate Company Business Records, 1888-1892
Series XXVI: Virginia Protection Life Insurance Company Journal A, 1874-1882
Series XXVII: Julius Meyer and Sons Business Records, 1888-1890
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
See also: Richmond City (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1861-1920 circa
Additional Richmond City (Va.) court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."
Contents List
- Bowman and Stroock Receipt Books, 1865-1867, 2 volumes
  Historical Information: Bowman and Stroock were wholesale jobbers of auction goods operating in New York and Richmond during the 1860s. By July 1868 the partnership was insolvent and involved in a Richmond Circuit Court suit against the Georgia Home Insurance Company, an assignee in Bowman and Stroock's bankruptcy.
  - Bowman and Stroock Receipt Books 1865-1867
- Clarkson Anderson and Company Ledger, 1859-1867, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Clarkson Anderson and Company operated in Richmond, Va., during the late nineteenth century.
  - Clarkson Anderson and Company Ledger 1859-1867
- Commonwealth Bank of Richmond Receivers' Cashbook, 1913-1917, 1 volume
  Historical Information: The Commonwealth Bank operated in Richmond, Va., during the early twentieth century. The bank was known as the Realty Bond and Trust Company before changing its name in 1906. In August 1913 the State Corporation Commission of Virginia placed control of the bank in the hands of receivers after determining that the bank was not fully observing the banking laws of the state. Generally, receivers are a neutral person appointed by the court to receive and preserve the property in litigation and to apply or dispose issues and profits at the direction of the court. James W. Gordon and John B. Lightfoot, Jr. were placed in charge of the bank's affairs and assets and were authorized to oversee the dissolution of the bank. The business of closing the Commonwealth Bank concluded in 1917.
  - Commonwealth Bank of Richmond Receivers' Cashbook 1913-1917
- First National Bank Ledger, 1871-1877, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Created in 1865, First National Bank was one of the first banks established in Virginia after the Civil War.
  - First National Bank Ledger 1871-1877
- Jacob Shook Daybook, 1828-1832, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Jacob Shook was a butcher and grocer operating in Richmond, Va., during the mid-nineteenth century.
  - Jacob Shook Daybook 1828-1832
- James Murphy Ledger, 1859-1873, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Born in Ireland, James Murphy was a soap and candle manufacturer in Richmond, Va. In the late 1860s, Murphy switched industries to become a retail grocer.
  - James Murphy Ledger 1859-1873
- Lisburn Land Company Minute Book, 1890-1901, 2 volumes
  Historical Information: Chartered in September 1890, the Lisburn Land Company purchased land to improve and sell in Richmond and Henrico County.
  - Lishburn Land Company Minute Book 1890-1901
- Mechanics Building Company Journal No. 3, 1877-1886, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Mechanics Building Company operated in Richmond, Va., during the late nineteenth century. Early board members of the company included Richmond area merchants Julius Ide and John A. Kratz.
  - Mechanics Building Company Journal No. 3 1877-1886
- National Auto Schools Corporation Stock Book, 1911, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Incorporated in May 1911, the National Auto Schools Corporation operated for a brief period in Richmond, Va.
  - National Auto Schools Corporation Stock Book 1911
- Old Dominion Electrical Construction Company Ledger, 1895-1896, 1 volume
  Historical Information: The Old Dominion Electrical Construction Company operated in Richmond, Va., during the 1890s. Maurice W. Thomas acted as the company's manager, and Maurice Hunter was its engineer. In early 1896 the company was placed under the control of receivers. Generally, receivers are neutral persons appointed by the court to receive and preserve the property in litigation and to apply or dispose issues and profits at the direction of the court.
  - Old Dominion Electrical Construction Company Ledger 1895-1896
- R.H. Boykin and Company Letterbook, 1895, 1 volume
  Historical Information: R.H. Boykin and Company was a tobacco manufacturing company located in Richmond, Virginia. Robert Hill Boykin was the primary partner. Boykin also served as the company's agent in Boston, Massachusetts.
  - R.H. Boykin and Company Letterbook 1895
- Richmond Wood Ware Manufacturing Company Business Records, 1894, 5 volumes
  Historical Information: The Richmond Wood Ware Manufacturing Company were contractors and builders specializing in builders' supplies, woodware, and tin and metal ware for household goods. The company was founded in April 1894, but after being plagued by business and financial problems the company closed its doors in October 1894. Officers for the company included John T. Terrell, president; J. L. Dickinson, vice president; and C. W. Honegger, secretary and treasurer.
  - Richmond Wood Ware Manufacturing Company Business Records 1894
- Robert Nowlan Macomber Checkbook, 1912-1914, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Robert Nowlan Macomber was a member of the Macomber family who were part owners in the Nowlan Company, a Richmond area jeweler. The Nowlan Company was established in 1850 in Petersburg by Thomas Nowlan. In 1866, Thomas Nowlan joined with partners Robert E. Macomber and Robert L. Winston and relocated the business to Richmond. For most of his adult life Robert Nowlan Macomber was a patient at Western State Hospital; however, he still held a claim on the Nowlan Company and his estate's funds were derived from the business.
  - Robert Nowlan Macomber Checkbook 1912-1914
- Samuel P. Lathrop Checkbook, 1878, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Originally from New York, Samuel P. Lathrop relocated to Richmond, Va., where he was a dry-goods merchant during the late nineteenth century.
  - Samuel P. Lathrop Checkbook 1878
- Turner Brooks and Company Account Book, 1869, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Turner Brooks and Company were tobacco merchants operating in Richmond, Va., during the mid-nineteenth century.
  - Turner Brooks and Company Account Book 1869
- Unidentified Cashbook, 1887-1889, 1 volume
  Historical Information: The unidentified business operated in Richmond, Va., during the late nineteenth century. It is possible that the business was Julius Meyer and Sons, a dry-goods firm in Richmond operated by German immigrant Julius Meyer and his sons Henry H., Alexander, and William Meyer.
  - Unidentified Cashbook 1887-1889
- Unidentified Cashbook, 1888-1891, 1 volume
  Historical Information: This unidentified business operated in Richmond, Va., during the late nineteenth century.
  - Unidentified Cashbook 1888-1891
- Unidentified Checkbook, 1865-1866, 1 volume
  Historical Information: This unidentified business operated in Richmond, Va., during the mid-nineteenth century.
  - Unidentified Checkbook, 1865-1866
- Unidentified Grocer Ledger, 1890, 1 volume
  Historical Information: This unidentified grocer operated in Richmond, Va., during the late nineteenth century.
  - Unidentified Grocer Ledger 1890
- Unidentified Ledger of Northern Accounts, 1890, 1 volume
  - Unidentified Ledger of Northern Accounts, 1890
- Unidentified Liquor Dealer Ledger, 1912-1913 Jacob Shook Daybook, 1912-1913, 1 volume
  Historical Information: This unidentified liquor dealer operated in the Richmond, Va., area during the early twentieth century.
  - Unidentified Liquor Dealer Ledger 1912-1913
- Unidentified Profit and Loss Ledger, 1911-1913, 1 volume
  Historical Information: This unidentified business operated in Richmond, Va., during the early twentieth century.
  - Unidentified Profit and Loss Ledger 1911-1913
- Unidentified Restaurant and Ice Cream Parlor Daybook, 1911, 1 volume
  Historical Information: This unidentified restaurant and ice cream parlor operated in Richmond, Va., during the early twentieth century.
  - Unidentified Restaurant and Ice Cream Parlor Daybook 1911
- Virginia Manufacturing and Trading Company Minute Book, 1882-1884, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Chartered in July 1882, the Virginia Manufacturing and Trading Company was engaged in the manufacturing and selling of cigars and cigarettes in Petersburg and Richmond, Virginia. The company sold George Campbell and Company's tobacco, cigars, and cigarettes and John H. Bryant and Company's Virginia sumac and quercitron bark. Officers of the company included J. R. Stebbins, president; George Campbell, general manager; and R. Colston, secretary and treasurer. After incurring debt and facing legal proceedings, the company dissolved in March 1884.
  - Virginia Manufacturing and Trading Company Minute Book 1882-1884
- Virginia Marl Phosphate Company Business Records, 1888-1892, 5 volumes and .10 cu. ft.
  Historical Information: Virginia Marl Phosphate Company was a fertilizer company located in Richmond, Virginia. It was formed 26 December 1888 and ceased active operations on 15 October 1894.
  - Virginia Marl Phosphate Company Business Records 1888-1892
- Virginia Protection Life Insurance Company Journal A, 1874-1882, 1 volume
  Historical Information: The Virginia Protection Life Insurance Company operated in Richmond, Va., during the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. At some point in its history the company changed its name to the Virginia Protective Life Insurance Company.
  - Virginia Protection Life Insurance Company Journal A, 1874-1882
- Julius Meyer and Sons Business Records, 1888-1890, 7 volumes
  Historical Information: Julius Meyer and Sons was a dry-goods business operating in Richmond, Va., during the late nineteenth century selling ready-made clothing, textiles, and household items. The mercantile firm consisted of German immigrant Julius Meyer and his sons Henry H., William, and Alexander Meyer.
  - Julius Meyer and Sons Business Records 1888-1890